[{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2019","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"P (Tiebreakers)","question":"1. This country’s capital was supposedly founded where an old woman discovered a floating koki tree filled with statues of Vishnu and the Buddha. That capital of this modern-day country was superseded in the 16th century by the city of Longvek, which was later sacked by the Kingdom of Ayutthaya (“ah-yoo-tah-YAH”). This country’s Land Chenla kingdom developed into an imperial state under Jayavarman II. The largest religious monument in the world is a temple complex in this country, which is featured on its flag and was built by this country’s medieval Khmer Empire. For 10 points, name this modern-day country home to Angkor Wat. ","answer":"ANSWER: Cambodia [or Kingdom of Cambodia; or Kampuchea] <World History> "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2019","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"P (Tiebreakers)","question":"2. Trimethylsilyl ether is commonly used as a protecting group for these compounds. DEADCAT deprotonates (“dee-PRO-tuh-nates”) these compounds after a nucleophilic attack by triphenylphosphine in the Mitsunobu reaction. Chromic acid reacts with one of these compounds in the first step of the Jones oxidation. An azeotrope is formed from 4% water and 96% of one of these molecules. The dehydration of these compounds produces an alkene, while their oxidation forms ketones. For 10 points, name these compounds with a hydroxyl group, exemplified by ethanol. ","answer":"ANSWER: alcohols [accept hydroxyl] <Chemistry> "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2019","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"P (Tiebreakers)","question":"8. The slow and quiet opening melody of the best-known piece by this composer alternates between pizzicato low strings and bassoons, then builds as its protagonist is chased by trolls. This composer included that piece after “Anitra’s Dance” in a suite that opens with the calm “Morning Mood.” For 10 points, name this composer whose “In the Hall of the Mountain King” closes his first Peer Gynt suite. ","answer":"ANSWER: Edvard Grieg <Classical Music> "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2019","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"P (Tiebreakers)","question":"4. At the end of one novel, a man calls the events in one of these places a “jolly good show” and compares it to an R. M. Ballantyne novel titled for a Coral one of these places. In one of these places home to a landmark called “the scar,” some characters reenact the chant “Cut her throat. Bash her in” after a hunt. One of these places is the central setting of a novel in which a pair of twins called Samneric join a tribe at Castle Rock. In a novel set in one of these places, Roger uses a boulder to crush the conch shell and Piggy, forcing Ralph to flee. For 10 points, name this kind of setting where a group of British schoolboys become stranded in Lord of the Flies. ","answer":"ANSWER: islands [prompt on forest or beach by asking “what larger location are they part of?”] <British Literature> "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2019","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"P (Tiebreakers)","question":"5. This man assisted director Nia DaCosta in handpicking Yahya Abdul-Mateen II for the 2020 Candyman reboot. After undergoing the Coagula procedure, Walter trains around the Armitage property to beat Jessie Owens in one film by this director. Addy is replaced by a “tethered” version of herself in a funhouse in this director’s most recent film, in which Hands Across America is a program harboring copies of the Wilsons. Hypnosis from a stirring teacup traps Daniel Kaluuya’s character in the “Sunken Place” in this man’s 2017 directorial debut. For 10 points, name this director of Us and Get Out, whose films are a stark departure from his comedy sketches with Keegan-Michael Key. ","answer":"ANSWER: Jordan Peele [or Jordan Haworth Peele] <CE/Geo/Other/Pop Culture> "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2019","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"P (Tiebreakers)","question":"6. The Vatican has condemned the worship of a folk saint popular in this country known as “the Bony Lady” or “Saint Death.” A church in this country was built on the hill where a saint appeared to a recent convert and asked him to pick up roses in his cloak. A legend from this country describes a “weeping woman” who is cursed to wander the Earth after drowning her children. In a myth from what is now this country, humanity was created out of bones, corn, and blood after those bones were stolen from the underworld by a “feathered serpent.” For 10 points, name this modern-day country home to La Llorona (“yo-RO-na”), the Virgin of Guadalupe, and the Aztec empire. ","answer":"ANSWER: Mexico <Mythology> "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2019","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"P (Tiebreakers)","question":"7. The core of a haplostele consists of this tissue, which contains pits and perforation plates. This tissue exudes its contents in a process called guttation. The Casparian strip in the endodermis prevents all substances from entering this tissue. Root pressure and cohesion–tension are bulk flow mechanisms of transporting the “sap” of this tissue, which consists of tapered tracheids (“TRAY-kee-ids”) and wider vessel elements. Transpirational pull increases surface tension promoting the primary function of this tissue. For 10 points, name this tissue that transports minerals and water in a plant, which is contrasted with sugar-carrying phloem. ","answer":"ANSWER: xylem [prompt on vascular tissue] <Biology> "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2019","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"P (Tiebreakers)","question":"8. A woman in a play by this author senses that the house “breathes forth slaughter” when she sees a man standing near the hearth. In a play by this author, a character argues that “the parent is he who mounts” since the mother is merely “nurse of the new-planted seed that grows.” A character created by this author dreams of giving birth to a snake, which suckles at her breast and bites off her nipple. The title character of another play by this author walks on purple tapestries before he is trapped in a net and murdered by Clytemnestra and her lover Aegisthus. For 10 points, name this ancient Greek tragedian of The Libation Bearers, The Eumenides, and Agamemnon, which form The Oresteia. ","answer":"ANSWER: Aeschylus <World/Other Literature> "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2019","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"P (Tiebreakers)","question":"9. A triangle juts into a circle of this color in a Constructivist poster by El Lissitzky. The artist painted over a Nazi armband that once featured in a painting titled for this color. A tilted square of this color on a background of a slightly different shade of this color comprise a “suprematist composition” by Kazimir Malevich. In a painting titled for this color, Jesus appears in front of a burning synagogue. It’s not yellow, but this color titles a crucifixion scene by Marc Chagall. This color symbolizes anti-communist forces in a Soviet poster in which it is “beaten” with the Red Wedge. For 10 points, name this color that, along with black, is present in most monochrome works? ","answer":"ANSWER: white [accept Beat the Whites with the Red Edge; accept White Crucifixion; accept White on White] <Painting/Sculpture> "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2019","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"P (Tiebreakers)","question":"8. For 10 points, give this name of two tsars, the latter of whom was the last Romanov ruler of Russia. ","answer":"ANSWER: Nicholas [accept Tsar Nicholas I or II; accept Nikolai or Nikolay] <European History> "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2019","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"P (Tiebreakers)","question":"1. The formation of these structures is associated with a high energy helicity index, or EHI. The NEXRAD (“nex-rad”) system allows for the algorithmic detection of these phenomena even without hook echo signatures. These structures begin to form upon the descent of a rear-flank downdraft with its associated mesocyclone. Though they can originate from squalls and tropical cyclones, these structures develop most commonly from supercells. The speed associated with these events is predicted by 28 damage indicators in the Enhanced Fujita Scale. The United States has an “alley” with an abundance of, for 10 points, what rapidly rotating columns of air? ","answer":"ANSWER: tornadoes <Other Science> "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2019","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"P (Tiebreakers)","question":"2. The death of Imre Lakatos kept him from contributing to a dialogue volume on this system. That book gives an “anything goes” proposal to abandon this system and advocates for “epistemological anarchism.” An early version of this process was proposed alongside a set of “Idols” of the Tribe, Cave, Marketplace, and Theatre that would impede its implementation. The verification principle has been superseded by Karl Popper’s suggestion to focus on what has been falsified by this process. The Novum Organum introduced Francis Bacon’s early version of this method, which he called “true induction.” For 10 points, name this system of making and testing hypotheses, used in biology and physics. ","answer":"ANSWER: scientific method [accept true induction until read; prompt on science; prompt on induction; prompt on research] (The first two lines refer to Paul Feyerabend’s Against Method.) <Philosophy> "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2019","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"P (Tiebreakers)","question":"3. In this state, tenant farmers rose up against its patroon system of feudal land ownership in the Anti-Rent War. The term “spoils system” originates with a quip by this state’s senator William Marcy about the nomination of its former governor to be Andrew Jackson’s minister to Britain. A political faction in this state which organized to oppose DeWitt Clinton became known as its capital’s namesake “Regency” and was led by a future vice president. Martin Van Buren hailed from this state, where he enjoyed support consistent support from Tammany Hall. For 10 points, name this mid-Atlantic state governed from Albany. ","answer":"ANSWER: New York <American History> "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2019","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"P (Tiebreakers)","question":"4. In a novel from this country, a poor farmer purchases a croft called Summerhouses, where he raises the bailiff’s granddaughter Asta as if she were his own child. An author from this country euhemerized (“yoo-HEEM-er-ized”) his ancestors’ deities by claiming that they were survivors of the sack of Troy. A genre of medieval epics set in this country typically describe blood feuds, and one of them is named for “Burnt Njál.” An author collected the myths of the culture that settled this island in a treatise on skaldic poetry called the “Younger” or “Prose” Edda. For 10 points, name this island country home to Halldor Laxness, Snorri Sturluson, and many Old Norse sagas. ","answer":"ANSWER: Iceland [or Ísland] <European Literature> "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2019","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"P (Tiebreakers)","question":"5. No encore followed this song, during which only a spotlight on the singer’s face would break the darkness in the room at Greenwich Village’s Cafe Society. A version of this song that eschews Sonny White’s standard accompaniment appears on Pastel Blues by Nina Simone. The book Lady Sings the Blues claims that this song’s music was written with Abel Meeropol, a Communist schoolteacher who evoked a “pastoral scene of the gallant South” where poplars smell of “magnolia” and “burning flesh” in its lyrics. Earlier, this song describes the “bulging eyes and the twisted mouth” of “bodies swinging in the summer breeze.” For 10 points, name this anti-lynching song, a signature of Billie Holiday. ","answer":"ANSWER: “Strange Fruit” <Other Arts> "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2019","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"P (Tiebreakers)","question":"6. At this period’s outset, one ruler received an opulent Netherlandish collection of cultural trinkets as part of the so-called “Dutch Gift.” During this period, the theatrical “Duke’s” and “King’s” companies competed to perform increasingly gaudy “spectaculars” named for this period. In contrast to its staunchly Puritan predecessor, this period saw the reintroduction of blood sports and raunchy comedies such as The Country Wife. At this period’s beginning, the Royal Society was founded, and Samuel Pepys (“peeps”) began his diary after Richard Cromwell’s failure as Lord-Protector. For 10 points, name this period of English history in which Charles II returned to England. ","answer":"ANSWER: English Restoration [accept descriptions of Charles II returning to the English throne until read, but prompt afterwards; do not accept or prompt on “Interregnum” or “English Civil War”] <European History> "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2019","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"P (Tiebreakers)","question":"7. The g-factor resulting from this phenomenon for an electron is slightly greater than two. A “crisis” about this quantity for a proton arose in 1987 and is still unsolved. Sigma one, sigma two, and sigma three denote Hermitian matrices that calculate this quantity named for Wolfgang Pauli. Silver atoms fired through an inhomogeneous magnetic field demonstrated that this value is quantized in an experiment conducted by Stern and Gerlach. This property has integer values for bosons and half-integer values for fermions. For 10 points, name this quantity, the intrinsic angular momentum of a particle. ","answer":"ANSWER: spin [prompt on (spin) angular momentum; do not accept or prompt on “momentum” or “orbital angular momentum” or “isospin”] <Physics> "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2019","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"P (Tiebreakers)","question":"8. This scholar’s claim that Hurricane Katrina was “a tragedy” but “also an opportunity” is cited in the introduction to Naomi Klein’s The Shock Doctrine. After Richard Nixon took the dollar off the gold standard, he repeated this thinker’s earlier remark that “we are all Keynesians (“CANE-zee-ins”) now.” This thinker suggested that the money supply be increased annually by a fixed “k-percent.” This neoliberal hosted the Free to Choose TV series, named for a book written with his wife Rose. This economist coined the name of a “miracle” in Augusto Pinochet’s country instituted in part by the “Chicago Boys” whom he once taught. For 10 points, name this Nobel-winning monetarist. ","answer":"ANSWER: Milton Friedman <Social Science> "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2019","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"P (Tiebreakers)","question":"9. A farmer suggests that a man who was thought to be dead abandoned this place to study law in “a distant part of the country,” leading him to become a “Justice of the Ten Pound Court.” A firm believer in Cotton Mather’s “History of New England Witchcraft” lives in this place, which is home to Major André’s tree. A horse named Gunpowder refuses to cross a bridge in a short story titled for this place, where a hat and a shattered pumpkin are found near a brook. In this glen near Tarry Town, Katrina Van Tassel marries Brom Bones after Ichabod Crane disappears. For 10 points, name this place that titles a Washington Irving short story featuring the Headless Horseman. ","answer":"ANSWER: Sleepy Hollow [accept “The Legend of Sleepy Hollow”; prompt on Greensburgh or New York; prompt on Tarry Town until read] <American Literature> "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2019","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"P (Tiebreakers)","question":"0. This practice is described between sections on sīla and paññā in a 5th-century treatise called the Visuddhimagga, which recommends 40 objects known as kammaṭṭhāna to be used for it. This practice is commonly used to cultivate the brahmavihārās, or “four immeasurable” virtues. Buddhists often divide this practice into two types: the temporary samatha form, and the “insight” form, vipassana. The last element of the Eightfold Path prescribes performing dhyāna, or this practice, to reach Nirvana. In Buddhist tradition, the performance of this practice is often guided by ānāpānasati, or mindful breathing. For 10 points, name this calming Buddhist practice, a general form of internal reflection. ","answer":"ANSWER: meditation [or word forms; accept introspection, reflection, or contemplation; accept samatha or vipassana or dhyāna until read, but prompt after; prompt on concentration or thinking] <Religion> Bonuses "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2019","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"P (Tiebreakers)","question":"[10] Name this branch of logic whose standard semantics were created by a teenaged Saul Kripke. This form of logic allows the expression of temporal conditions, obligation, and possibility. ","answer":"ANSWER: modal logic "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2019","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"P (Tiebreakers)","question":"[10] In modal logic, a square often represents this modality, which is equivalent to saying that a proposition is “not possibly false.” The statement “p if and only if q” holds true only if q both has this quality and is sufficient for p. ","answer":"ANSWER: necessity [or necessary; or word forms] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2019","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"P (Tiebreakers)","question":"[10] One of these animals is “on the mat” in a common sample statement used in modal logic. In a thought experiment by Erwin Schrödinger, one of these animals is said to be simultaneously alive and dead. ","answer":"ANSWER: cats [or synonyms like felines; accept “the cat is on the mat”; accept Schrödinger’s cat] <Philosophy> "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2019","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"P (Tiebreakers)","question":"[10] Name this construct proposed by Charles Spearman central to his “two-factor theory” of a certain ability. The Raven Progressive Matrices test “loads onto,” or heavily correlates with, this psychometric factor. ","answer":"ANSWER: g-factor [or general intelligence factor; or general mental ability; accept g-loading; prompt on intelligence; prompt on IQ] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2019","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"P (Tiebreakers)","question":"[10] A controversy over the heritability of IQ, and more specifically the g-factor, erupted on account of a Murray and Herrnstein book named for this shape. IQ’s normal distribution is graphed as a “curve” named for this object. ","answer":"ANSWER: The Bell Curve [or bells] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2019","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"P (Tiebreakers)","question":"[10] This thinker attacked craniometry and IQ testing in general for trying to “reify” intelligence under the framework of biological determinism in The Mismeasure of Man. This paleontologist also wrote The Panda’s Thumb. ","answer":"ANSWER: Stephen Jay Gould <Social Science> "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2019","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"P (Tiebreakers)","question":"[10] Name this poet who wrote the travel diary The Narrow Road to the Deep North. ","answer":"ANSWER: Matsuo Bashō "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2019","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"P (Tiebreakers)","question":"[10] Bashō wrote one of these poems about a frog jumping into a pond. Poems in this Japanese form have three lines consisting of five, seven, and five syllables. ","answer":"ANSWER: haiku "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2019","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"P (Tiebreakers)","question":"[10] A frog leaps into a brazier (“BRAY-zhur”) in one anecdote from this zuihitsu (“ZOO-ee-heet-soo”) work, which includes lists of “hateful things” and “things that make one’s heart beat faster.” ","answer":"ANSWER: The Pillow Book [or Makura no Sōshi] (by Sei Shōnagon) <World/Other Literature> "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2019","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"P (Tiebreakers)","question":"[10] Name this type of algorithm that, in an interactive proof system, is contrasted with an unreliable Prover with unlimited power. These algorithms rely on certificates to check the validity of a proposed solution to a problem. ","answer":"ANSWER: verifiers "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2019","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"P (Tiebreakers)","question":"[10] All languages in this complexity class have interactive proofs, as the Prover can simply return a polynomial-size certificate to the Verifier. This class is contrasted with the class of problems solvable in polynomial time. ","answer":"ANSWER: NP [accept nondeterministic polynomial time; prompt on nondeterministic polynomial] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2019","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"P (Tiebreakers)","question":"[10] The Interactive Proof complexity class, or IP, contains the complement of the isomorphism problem of these mathematical structures, which are composed of vertices and edges. ","answer":"ANSWER: graphs [accept graph isomorphism problem] <Other Science> "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2019","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"P (Tiebreakers)","question":"1. This famed orgy was named for the objects that “fifty honest prostitutes” attempted to pick up off the floor while crawling between flaming candles. ","answer":"ANSWER: the Banquet of the Chestnuts [both parts are necessary; or the Ballet of the Chestnuts] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2019","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"P (Tiebreakers)","question":"[10] Johann Burchard’s implausible account of the Banquet of the Chestnuts was likely embellished to attack Pope Alexander VI, a member of this family, which also included the rumor-haunted Lucrezia among its numbers. ","answer":"ANSWER: House of Borgia [or Borja] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2019","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"P (Tiebreakers)","question":"[10] Cesare Borgia (“CHEZ-ah-ray BOR-juh”) served as the direct inspiration for this early modern political treatise, an analysis of statecraft and government written by Niccolò Macchiavelli. ","answer":"ANSWER: The Prince [or Il Principe; or De Principatibus; or Of Principalities] <European History> "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2019","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"P (Tiebreakers)","question":"[10] Name this character. A woman describes kissing this character at Bourton as “the most exquisite moment of her whole life.” ","answer":"ANSWER: Sally Seton [accept either name; accept Lady Rosseter] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2019","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"P (Tiebreakers)","question":"[10] This author, who was in love with Madge Vaughan as a teenager, created Sally Seton in Mrs. Dalloway. ","answer":"ANSWER: Virginia Woolf [or Adeline Virginia Woolf] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2019","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"P (Tiebreakers)","question":"[10] Woolf also wrote this novel inspired by her lover, Vita Sackville-West. This novel’s gender-changing protagonist lives for over three hundred years and has an affair with Elizabeth I. ","answer":"ANSWER: Orlando: A Biography <British Literature> "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2019","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"P (Tiebreakers)","question":"[10] Name this Swiss-Italian artist, whose Walking Man and Pointing Man sculptures depict his trademark style of extremely thin, spindly figures. ","answer":"ANSWER: Alberto Giacometti "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2019","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"P (Tiebreakers)","question":"[10] This other sculptor’s Walking Man intentionally lacks arms and a head. This artist’s sculptures The Kiss and The Thinker were originally part of his Gates of Hell. ","answer":"ANSWER: Auguste Rodin [or François Auguste René Rodin] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2019","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"P (Tiebreakers)","question":"[10] Rodin’s Walking Man inspired a member of this artistic movement to sculpt Unique Forms of Continuity in Space. This early 20th-century movement celebrated the dynamism and speed of new technology. ","answer":"ANSWER: Futurism [or Futurismo; or Futurist] <Painting/Sculpture> "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2019","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"P (Tiebreakers)","question":"[10] Name this Christian empire in East Africa ruled by the Solomonic dynasty. It was known in the west as Abyssinia. ","answer":"ANSWER: Ethiopia "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2019","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"P (Tiebreakers)","question":"[10] In the 1530s, much of northern Ethiopia was overrun by the Muslim Adal Sultanate, but was later liberated with the help of this European power that dispatched troops under Cristóvão da Gama. ","answer":"ANSWER: Portugal (Cristóvão da Gama was the son of Vasco de Gama.) "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2019","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"P (Tiebreakers)","question":"[10] Portuguese envoys to Ethiopia widely conflated it with the kingdom of this mythical Nestorian Christian ruler of the east. Earlier, this figure was believed to rule in India or Central Asia. ","answer":"ANSWER: Prester John [or Presbyter John; prompt on John or John the Elder] <World History> "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2019","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"P (Tiebreakers)","question":"[10] Name this figure who is symbolically pelted with rocks by Ibrāhīm in a ritual inspired by his fruitless attempt to stop the sacrifice of Ismā‘īl. In the Quran, this figure was the only one who refused to bow to Adam. ","answer":"ANSWER: the Devil [or Satan; accept Stoning of the Devil; accept Shayṭān, Shayāṭīn, or Šayṭān; accept Iblīs] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2019","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"P (Tiebreakers)","question":"[10] The Stoning of the Devil is performed on this Islamic holiday that commemorates Ibrāhīm’s aforementioned resolve. This holiday includes massive animal sacrifices. ","answer":"ANSWER: Eid al-Adha [or Eid Qurban; or Eid al-Kabir; accept Bakr-Eid or Bakrid; prompt on Festival of the Sacrifice; prompt on Eid; do not accept or prompt on “Eid al-Fitr”] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2019","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"P (Tiebreakers)","question":"[10] Eid al-Adha also marks the end of this Islamic ritual, whose performers typically circumambulate the Kaaba seven times. All able-bodied Muslims are mandated to perform this pilgrimage to Mecca at least once. ","answer":"ANSWER: Hajj <Religion> "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2019","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"P (Tiebreakers)","question":"[10] Name this property that occurs in crystals with no inversion center. Materials possess with this property generate a potential difference under mechanical stress. ","answer":"ANSWER: piezoelectricity [or piezoelectric effect] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2019","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"P (Tiebreakers)","question":"[10] Crystals of this mineral exhibit piezoelectricity, leading to its common use in watches. This mineral consists of silicon and oxygen. ","answer":"ANSWER: quartz "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2019","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"P (Tiebreakers)","question":"[10] Quartz makes a good crystal oscillator due to its high value for this quantity, which describes how underdamped an oscillator is. It is defined as the resonator frequency divided by the resonance bandwidth. ","answer":"ANSWER: Q factor [or quality factor] <Physics> "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2019","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"P (Tiebreakers)","question":"[10] Name this [emphasize] main profession of a character who replies, “The saints and poets, maybe—they do some” after a woman concludes, “Oh, earth, you’re too wonderful for anyone to realize you.” ","answer":"ANSWER: stage manager [or stage director; prompt on manager] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2019","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"P (Tiebreakers)","question":"[10] The Stage Manager introduces the people of Grover’s Corners in the play Our Town, which was written by this author of The Skin of Our Teeth. ","answer":"ANSWER: Thornton Wilder [or Thornton Niven Wilder] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2019","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"P (Tiebreakers)","question":"[10] After reliving this event from her life in the play’s final scene, Emily Webb asks the Stage Manager, “Do any human beings ever realize life while they live it?” ","answer":"ANSWER: her twelfth birthday <American Literature> "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2019","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"P (Tiebreakers)","question":"[10] Name this conductor who was fond of conducting with his eyes closed. This longtime director of the Berlin Philharmonic was bitter rivals with his predecessor, Wilhelm Furtwängler. ","answer":"ANSWER: Herbert von Karajan (“KAR-ah-yahn”) "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2019","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"P (Tiebreakers)","question":"[10] Karajan was controversially a member of this political party. Richard Strauss briefly worked in its State Music Institute, which otherwise denigrated “degenerate” jazz and atonal music in favor of Brahms and Wagner. ","answer":"ANSWER: Nazi Party [or NSDAP; or National Socialist German Workers’ Party] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2019","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"P (Tiebreakers)","question":"[10] Because he really wanted to take a nice cover photo, Karajan refused to record a second take of a lackluster version of this composer’s Triple Concerto. His other concerti include one for violin in D major and one for piano called “Emperor.” ","answer":"ANSWER: Ludwig van Beethoven <Classical Music> "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2019","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"P (Tiebreakers)","question":"[10] Name this French-speaking country that U.S. forces occupied in 1915 after its president Vilbrun Guillaume Sam was toppled and killed. ","answer":"ANSWER: Haiti [or Republic of Haiti] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2019","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"P (Tiebreakers)","question":"[10] The US occupation of Haiti was ordered by this president, who also ordered military interventions into the Dominican Republic, Cuba, Honduras, and Mexico. He won reelection in 1916 with the slogan “He kept us out of war.” ","answer":"ANSWER: Woodrow Wilson [or Thomas Woodrow Wilson] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2019","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"P (Tiebreakers)","question":"[10] U.S. forces withdrew from Haiti and other Latin American countries under this policy promoted by Franklin Roosevelt that encouraged peaceful cooperation in the Americas. ","answer":"ANSWER: Good Neighbor policy <American History> "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2019","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"P (Tiebreakers)","question":"[10] Name these chemical species with an unpaired valence electron, which generally makes them extremely reactive. ","answer":"ANSWER: free radical "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2019","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"P (Tiebreakers)","question":"[10] The most common form of this element, its triplet form, is a stable diradical. MO theory can be used to explain why that form of this element is paramagnetic. ","answer":"ANSWER: oxygen [or O2 ] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2019","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"P (Tiebreakers)","question":"[10] This heterocyclic compound, discovered by Lebedev and Kazarnowskii, is a stable radical partially because it has four methyl groups adjacent to an aminoxyl group. This molecule can catalyze primary alcohol oxidation. ","answer":"ANSWER: TEMPO [or (2,2,6,6-tetramethylpiperidin-1-yl)oxyl] <Chemistry> "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2019","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"P (Tiebreakers)","question":"[10] Name this god. In the usual account, this god is killed inadvertently by his blind brother with a sprig of sharpened mistletoe. ","answer":"ANSWER: Baldr "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2019","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"P (Tiebreakers)","question":"[10] Although Snorri attributes Baldr’s death to Loki’s malice, Dronke argues that he was killed intentionally as a sacrifice to this god, possibly to ensure the world’s rejuvenation after Ragnarök. This wise leader of the Æsir is known as the “Allfather.” ","answer":"ANSWER: Odin "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2019","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"P (Tiebreakers)","question":"[10] In support of Dronke’s theory, Heather O’Donoghue proposes that Snorri borrowed the mytheme of a blind shooter from a Jewish legend in which this blind man accidentally kills Cain. This man tells his wives Adah and Zillah that since Cain was avenged sevenfold, surely he would be avenged “seventy and sevenfold.” ","answer":"ANSWER: Lamech (“LAY-mick”) <Mythology> "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2019","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"P (Tiebreakers)","question":"[10] Name this person. Antonio Machado described this person as having “blood on his brow and lead in his guts” in the poem “The Crime was in Granada,” where this person was executed by fascists. ","answer":"ANSWER: Federico García Lorca [prompt on García] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2019","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"P (Tiebreakers)","question":"[10] The name “Federico” is listed after “Raúl” and “Rafael” in this author’s poem “I Explain a Few Things.” This communist joined the International Brigades to fight in the Spanish Civil War and frequently used green ink. ","answer":"ANSWER: Pablo Neruda "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2019","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"P (Tiebreakers)","question":"[10] This author asked “and you, Garcia Lorca, what were you doing down by the watermelons” in his poem “A Supermarket in California.” He also wrote “Howl.” ","answer":"ANSWER: Allen Ginsberg <European Literature> "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2019","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"P (Tiebreakers)","question":"[10] Name this film, which was directed by Luis Buñuel. This plotless 1929 short film includes a sequence featuring dead donkeys atop grand pianos, and is a major work of surrealist cinema. ","answer":"ANSWER: Un Chien Andalou [or An Andalusian Dog] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2019","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"P (Tiebreakers)","question":"[10] Buñuel co-wrote the screenplay for Un Chien Andalou with this other Spanish surrealist, who painted The Persistence of Memory. ","answer":"ANSWER: Salvador Dalí "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2019","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"P (Tiebreakers)","question":"[10] In one scene of Un Chien Andalou, a man dressed as a nun falls off one of these things while a woman watches from her window. In a neorealist film, a man pawns his family’s bed sheets to buy one of these things. ","answer":"ANSWER: bicycles [or bikes] (The second film is Bicycle Thieves.) <Other Arts> "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2019","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"P (Tiebreakers)","question":"[10] Name this member of the Heptarchy that initially formed from the Anglian kingdoms of Deira and Bernicia. This kingdom lost the Battles of Maserfield and Hatfield Chase to a neighboring state led by Penda. ","answer":"ANSWER: Kingdom of Northumbria "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2019","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"P (Tiebreakers)","question":"1. ","answer":"ANSWER: Venerable Bede [accept Saint Bede; accept Baeda] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2019","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"P (Tiebreakers)","question":"3. These Scandinavian military campaigns often utilized so-called “berserkers” who travelled by longship. ","answer":"ANSWER: Viking raids [accept attacks, invasions, incursions, or synonyms in place of “raids”; accept Norsemen, Norwegians, Danes, or Danish people in place of “Vikings”; prompt on answers mentioning raids by Swedes or Swedish people; prompt on heathens in place of “Vikings”] <European History> "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2019","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"P (Tiebreakers)","question":"[10] Name this word, contrasted with recessive, which describes alleles that mask the effect of the same gene on the other chromosome. ","answer":"ANSWER: dominant [or dominance] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2019","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"P (Tiebreakers)","question":"[10] Unlike dominance, this interaction is exhibited when alleles mask the effect of genes at [emphasize] another locus. For example, the allele for albinism supersedes alleles for skin pigment. ","answer":"ANSWER: epistasis [accept epistatic allele] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2019","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"P (Tiebreakers)","question":"1. ","answer":"ANSWER: penetrance <Biology> "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2019","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"P (Tiebreakers)","question":"[10] Name this non-US region where the Tourtière meat pie is served alongside this region’s unique Bûche Lambert ice cream yule log as part of Réveillon celebrations. ","answer":"ANSWER: Québec "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2019","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"P (Tiebreakers)","question":"[10] This Quebecois comfort meal consists of a dish of cheese curds and french fries covered with gravy. This dish, voted the national food of Canada, sparked American imitations like “disco fries.” ","answer":"ANSWER: poutine [accept pot poutine or raspoutine] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2019","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"P (Tiebreakers)","question":"[10] Another Canadian delicacy is muktuk, an Inuit dish primarily made from the skin and blubber of this animal. The holiday Nalukataq marks the end of the spring hunting season of these animals amongst the Inupiaq in Alaska. ","answer":"ANSWER: whales [accept bowhead whale] <CE/Geo/Other/Pop Culture>"}]
